Register of the South African subject collection
Hoover Institution Archives
South African Subject collection
1910-2007
XX789
Hoover Institution Archives
65 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 9 phonorecords, 10 phonotape cassettes, 1 phonotape reel, 18 videotape cassettes. (31.0 linear feet)
Pamphlets, serial issues, reports, leaflets, election campaign literature, flyers, newsletters, other printed matter, letters, sound recordings and video tapes, relating to political, social and economic conditions, apartheid and race relations, and elections in South Africa; revolutionary movements in South Africa, especially the African National Congress; international support groups, especially in the United States, for such movements; and campus movements in the United States protesting investment in South Africa.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
African National Congress.; Africa.; Audiotapes.; Elections--South Africa.; Guerrillas--South Africa.; Phonorecords.; Radicalism--United States.; South Africa--Economic conditions.; South Africa--Politics and government--20th century.; South Africa--Race relations.; South Africa--Social conditions--1961-.; South Africa.; Student movements--United States.; United States--Foreign relations.; Universities and colleges--United States.; Video tapes.
- GENERAL SUBJECT FILE, 1945-1995
  Scope and Contents note
  Articles, brochures, clippings, ephemera, flyers, newspapers, pamphlets, reports and speeches relating to economic, political and social conditions in South Africa. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General (Box 1, 29)
    - General
    - Agriculture
    - Asika, Ukpabi
    - Athletics
    - Biko, Stephen Bantu
    - Buthelezi, Mangosuthu Gatsha
    - Chikane, Reverend Frank
    - Children (Box 2, 29-30)
    - Clippings and articles
    - Comic strips
    - Conscription
    - Defense
      - Detention
      - Harms Commission
      - Nuclear capability
      - South African Police
      - South African Security Forces
    - Ecology
    - Environment
    - Health
      - General
      - Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS)
    - Housing
    - History
    - Homelessness
    - Justice and the judicial system
    - Mandela, Nelson
    - Mandela, Winnie (Box 3, 30)
    - Nkosi Sikelele iAfrika (African National Anthem)
    - Operation Real South Africa
      - Kwa Nobuhle
      - Langa Diary
      - Red Location Removal
    - Paton, Alan
    - Personal reflections - Letter from the Cape
    - Race and racism
      - South African Bureau of Racial Affairs
      - South African Institute of Race Relations
    - Religion
      - General
      - Church involvement in South African politics
    - South African Broadcasting Corporation
      - 1987
      - 1988
      - 1989 (Box 4, 30)
      - 1990 and 1992
    - South African Institute of International Affairs
    - Sports
    - Sun City
    - Townships
      - Alexandra
      - Soweto
        - General
        - South Africa Community Projects, Ltd.
    - Transvaal
    - Tutu, Bishop Desmond
      - General
        - General
        - Speeches
      - Bishop Desmond Tutu Southern African Refugee Scholarship Fund
    - Women
    - Zulu nation
  - Economics (Box 5, 30)
    - General
    - Clippings and articles
    - Corporations
      - General
      - Small Business Development Corporation Limited
    - Foreign aid
    - Guest workers
    - Homelands - Bophuthatswana
    - Labor
    - Mining
    - Sanctions (see also Foreign relations - United States)
    - Strikes
    - Sullivan principle
  - Education
    - General (Box 6, 31)
    - General
    - All Schools for All People Campaign
    - Education Fund for Southern Africa
    - English Literacy Project
    - National Education Council
    - National Education Union of South Africa (NEUSA)
    - New Unity Movement
    - Rand Afrikaans University
    - Rhodes University
    - Teacher Opportunity Program
    - Union of Democratic University Staff Associations
    - University of Bophuthatswana
    - University of Cape Town (see also Organizations) (Box 6, 31)
      - General
      - Circulars
      - Clippings
      - Correspondence
      - Newspapers
        - Comment
        - Varsity
      - Printed matter
    - University of Durban Westville
    - University of Natal (see also Organizations)
    - University of the Orange Free State
    - University of Pretoria
    - University of South Africa
    - University Teachers' Association of South Africa (UTASA)
    - University of Western Cape Organizations)
    - University of the Witwatersrand (see also (Box 7, 31)
  - Elections
    - General
    - 1987 May 6
      - General
      - Conservative Party
      - Herstigte Nasionale Party (HNP)
      - Independent Party
      - National Party
      - Progressive Federal Party (PFP)
      - United Democratic Front (UDF)
      - United Party (UP)
    - 1988 October 26
      - General
      - Conservative Party
      - National Party
      - Progressive Federal Party (PFP)
    - 1989 September 6 (Box 8, 31)
      - Democratic Party
      - National Party
      - Progressive Federal Party (PFP)
  - Foreign relations
    - Ethiopia
    - Europe
    - India
    - Indian community in South Africa
    - Israel
    - United Kingdom
    - United Nations
    - United States
      - General
        - General. Statements and testimony before Congress regarding United States foreign and economic policies towards South Africa
        - Congressional Research Service. Includes publications on sanctions, the African National Congress and United States economic and political relationship with South Africa
        - United States-South Africa Leader Exchange Program
      - United Nations
  - Organizations
    - General
      - General
      - Council for Black Education and Research
      - Health and Refugee Trust of South Africa
      - Market Theatre Foundation Africa
      - Organization for Appropriate Social Services in South (Box 9, 31)
      - South African Voluntary Service
      - Southern African Forum
    - Economic
      - General
      - Association for Rural Advancement
      - Free Market Foundation of Southern Africa
      - Get Ahead Foundation
      - Media Workers Association
      - South Africa Foundation
      - South African Clothing and Textile Worker's Union
      - Southern African Research Service
      - Worker's Organization for Socialist Action (WOSA)
    - Political and human rights
      - General
      - Afrikaner-Weerstandsbeweging (AWB)
      - Amnesty International
      - Anti-Apartheid Bewegung
      - Anti-Censorship Action Group (ACAG)
      - Association for Rural Advancement (Box 10, 31-32)
      - Azanian People's Organization (AZAPO)
      - Black Consciousness Movement of Azania (BCMA)
      - Black Sash
      - Blanke Bevrydingsbeweging van Suid Afrika
      - Coca-Cola Company
      - Christian Institute of Southern Africa - Program for Social Change
      - David Webster Funeral Committee
      - Defence of Democracy Trust
      - Detention Action Committee
      - Detainees Aid Committee
      - Detainees' Parents Support Committee
      - Detainees' Parents Support Group
      - End Conscription Campaign (ECC)
      - Five Freedoms Forum (Box 11, 32)
      - Free the Children Alliance
      - Free Mandela Movement
      - Fund for a Free South Africa
      - Groundswell
      - Human Awareness Programme
      - Human Rights Commission
      - Human Rights Committee of South Africa
      - Human Rights Trust
      - Inkatha Movement
      - Institute for a Democratic Alternative for South Africa (IDASA)
      - International Freedom Foundation (South African branch)
      - Jews for Social Justice
      - Johannesburg Democratic Action Committtee (JODAC)
      - Johannesburg Youth Congress (JOYCO)
      - KwaZulu Natal Indaba
      - Lawyers for Human Rights
      - Legal Resources Center
      - National Democratic Movement
      - National Forum Committee
      - Nelson Mandela International Reception Committee
      - Society for the Abolition of the Death Penalty in South Africa
      - South African Human Rights Commitee
      - South African Media Council
      - South African Youth Congress
      - Soweto Civic Association
      - Terrorism Research Center
      - Union of Black Journalists (UBJ)
      - Veterans for Victory
      - Washington Office on Africa
      - Women's Legal Status Committee (WLSC)
    - Religious (Box 12, 32)
      - Catholic Bishops' Conference
      - Federation of the Covenant People
      - Pietermaritzburg Agency for Christian Social Awareness (PACSA)
      - Relevant Pentecostal Witness
      - South African Council of Churches
      - World Council of Churches
    - Student
      - General
        - General
        - University of Cape Town
        - University of Witwatersrand
      - Azanian Students Organization (AZASO)
      - Black Student Society (BSS)
        - University of Cape Town
        - University of Witwatersrand
      - Christian Awareness - University of Witwatersrand
      - Economic Research Council (ERC) - University of Witwatersrand
      - Moderate Student Movement - University of Witwatersrand
      - Muslim Students' Association - University of Witwatersrand
      - National Student Federation
      - National Union of South African Students (NUSAS) (Box 13, 32)
        - General
        - University of Witwatersrand
      - Socialist Students' Action Committee
      - South African Students' Organization (SASO)
        - General
        - Bulletins
        - Reports
      - SASPOST - a newsletter of opportunities and information for South African students in North America
      - South African Union of Jewish Students (SAUJS) - University of Witwatersrand (Box 14, 32)
      - Soweto Students Congress
      - Student Action Front - University of Natal
      - Student Community Action News
      - Students for a Free South Africa
      - Student Moderate Alliance - University of Witwatersrand
      - Student Representative Council (SRC)
        - Rhodes University
        - Stanford University
        - Soweto
        - University of Cape Town
          - General
          - SRC News
          - Wages Commission
            - General
            - Reports
            - Work committees
        - University of Natal
        - University of Witwatersrand
          - General
          - Academic Freedom Committee
          - Projects Committee
          - SRC News
          - Wages Commission
      - Student Teaching and Education Programm (STEP) - University of Witwatersrand
      - Students for a Free South Africa
      - University of Stellenbosch
      - University of Western Cape
      - Wits Libertarian Society - University of Witwatersrand
      - Wits Women's Movement - University of Witwatersrand
  - Trade unions (Box 15, 32-33)
    - General
    - Azanian Confederation of Trade Unions (AZACTU)
    - Commercial Catering and Allied Workers' Union of South Africa (CCAWUSA)
    - Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU)
    - Congress of South African Writers
    - Council of Unions of South Africa
    - National Union of Mine Workers (NUM)
    - Post and Telecommunications Workers Association (POTWA)
    - Progressive Engineers
    - Sarmcol Workers Co-operative (SAWCO)
    - South African Congress of Trade Unions (SACTU)
    - South African Democratic Teachers Union (SADTU)
    - South African Domestic Workers Union (SADWU)
    - Vereniging van Oranjewerkers
  - Political parties (Box 16, 33-35)
    - African Christian Democratic Party (ACDF)
    - Africa Muslim Party
    - Communist Party
    - Conservative Party
    - Democratic Party
    - Dikwankwetla Party
    - Federal Party
    - Freedom Front
    - Green Party
    - Herstigte Nasionale Party (HNP)
    - Independent Party
    - Inkatha Freedom Party
    - Kiss Party
    - Luso-South African Party (LUSAP)
    - Merit Party
    - National Party
    - New Republic Party
    - Progressive Federal Party
    - Soccer Party
    - Sofasonke
    - South African Communist Party (SACP)
    - South African Progressive Reform Party
    - United Democratic Front
    - United Party
    - Workers' List Party
    - Ximoko Progressive Party
  - Politics and government
    - General
    - Apartheid
    - Botha, Pieter W. - speeches and statements
    - Citizenship (Box 17, 35)
      - General
        - General
        - Clippings
        - Press releases and statements
        - Reports
      - Communism/Marxism
      - Constitution
      - Convention for a Democratic South Africa (CODESA)
      - Death penalty
      - Embassy of South Africa, Washington, D.C.
      - Group Areas Act
      - Homelands
        - General
        - Basutoland
        - Bophuthatswana
        - Kwazulu
        - Maputaland
        - Transkei
        - Transvaal Rural Action Committee
      - Klerk, Frederik Willem de
      - National Peace Accord, 1991 September 14
      - Negotiations
      - Patriotic/United Front Conference, 1991 October 25-27 (Box 18, 35)
      - Referendum
      - Resettlement program
      - South African Citizenship Act, No. 44 of, 1949
- INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT GROUPS, 1961-1993
  Brochures, calendars, ephemera, newsletters and pamphlets relating to international involvement in the issue of apartheid in South Africa. Arranged alphabetically by title of organization. Relates to international involvement in South Africa and to some extent southern Africa in general. Consult African Subject Collection for additional material.
  - General (Box 18, 35)
  - Accuracy in Media (AIM)
  - Action Against Apartheid
  - Africa Fund
  - Africa Groups of Sweden
  - Africa Information Service
  - Africa Research Group
  - Afrikagrupperna i Sverige. Includes material on Namibia
  - Americans Against Apartheid (Box 19, 35-36)
  - Anti-Apartheid Movement (London)
    - General. Includes materials on Namibia
    - British corporations in South Africa
    - British Industry Committee on South Africa (BICSA)
    - Conference papers
    - Minutes
    - Newsletters
    - Printed matter
    - South Africa the Imprisoned Society (SATIS)
  - Bay Area Anti-Apartheid Network (BAAAN)
  - Bay Area Free South Africa Movement
  - Bevrijdingsfonds Komitee Zuidelijk Afrika
  - Bishop Ambrose Reeves Trust (BART)
  - British Defense and Aid Fund for Southern Africa
  - Catholic Institute for International Relations (CIIR)
  - Canada - South Africa Cooperation (CSAC)
  - Cape Democrats
  - Cape Youth Congress
  - Centre for Policy Studies
  - Christianity and Crisis
  - Clergy and Laity Concerned
  - Comite Anti-Apartheid de Madrid
  - Comite Contre le Colonialisme et L'Apartheid, Brussels, Belgium
  - Committee on South African War Resistance (COSAWR)
  - Conscientious Objectors Support Group (COSG) Democracy
  - Council for the Defense of Freedom - Alliance for African (Box 20, 36)
  - Covenant Against Apartheid Home and Abroad Program
  - Episcopal Churchpeople for South Africa (formerly Episcopal Churchmen for South Africa). Includes material on Namibia
    - 1961-1976
    - 1977-1986
  - European Campaign Against South African Aggression on Mozambique and Angola (ECASAAMA)
  - Free South Africa Labor Committee
  - Get Ahead Foundation
  - Holland Committee on Southern Africa
  - Informationsdienst Sudliches Afrika
  - International Business Machines (IBM) Workers United
  - International Commission of Jurists
  - International Committee Against Apartheid, Racism and Colonialism in Southern Africa. Includes material on Namibia
  - International Defense and Aid Fund for Southern Africa
  - International University Exchange Fund
  - Japan Anti-Apartheid Committee: Tokyo
  - Komitee Sudliches Afrika. Includes material on Portugal's African colonies
  - Lawyers Against Apartheid
  - Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law. Includes material on Namibia
  - League of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies
  - Liberation Support Movement
    - Calendars
    - Pamphlets (Box 21, 36-37)
  - National Committee Against Apartheid (NACAP - Nigeria)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ. Includes material on other countries of southern Africa
  - Netherlands Anti-Apartheid Movement
  - Oakland-Africa Sister-Cities International
  - Project Committee
  - Project South Africa
  - Revolutionary Communist Party U.S.A.
  - San Francisco Anti-Apartheid Committee
  - South Africa Crisis Coordinating Committee
  - South Africa Freedom Fund
  - South Africa Support Project
  - South African Institute of Race Relations
  - South African Rugby Tour
  - South African War Resisters
  - Southern Africa Coalition
  - Southern African Forum
  - Southern African News Agency (SANA)
  - Stanford Students for a Free South Africa
  - Third World Resources. Includes material on other countries of Southern Africa
  - TransAfrica
  - United States Information Agency (USIA)
  - United States League of Revolutionary Struggle (M-L)
  - United States-South Africa Sister Community Project
  - Washington Office on Africa
  - Young Americans for Freedom
- REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENTS, circa 1943-1993
  Articles, clippings, communiques, ephemera, pamphlets, press releases, reports, speeches and statements primarily relating to revolutionary activities of the African National Congress and the Pan Africanist Congress of Azania. Arranged alphabetically by name of movement.
  - General (Box 21, 36-37)
    - General
      - Printed matter
      - Reports
    - Freedom Charter
  - African National Congress (ANC)
    - General
      - General
      - Bibliography (Box 22, 37-38)
      - Briefing
      - Clippings and articles
      - Flyers
      - Memoranda
      - Messages
      - Minutes of meetings
      - Newsletters
      - Pamphlets
      - Press conference
      - Press releases
      - Printed matter
      - Reports
      - Speeches
      - Statements and communiques
        - General
        - National Executive Committee of the African National Congress
    - Economic policy
    - Mandela, Nelson
    - Solomon Mahlangu Freedom College
    - Tambo, Oliver
    - Women
    - Miscellany
  - Azanian People's Liberation Army (APLA)
  - Black Consciousness Movement of Azania
  - Coloured People's Congress (CPC)
  - Pan Africanist Congress of Azania (PAC of Azania)
    - General
      - General
      - Brochure
      - Bulletins (Box 23, 39)
      - Clippings and articles
      - Communique
      - Newsletters
      - Pamphlets
      - Speech
      - Policies and principles of the PAC
      - Press releases and statements
    - Legal status of the South African government as viewed by the PAC
    - Mlambo, Johnson Philip. Speeches
    - National Executive Committee of the PAC of Azania
    - Pokela, John Nyati
      - General
      - Speeches and statements
    - Sharpeville
    - Sobukwe, Mangaliso Robert
      - General
      - Statement
    - Women
- INTERNATIONAL INVESTMENT AND DIVESTMENT IN SOUTH AFRICA, 1971-1986
  Brochures, newsletters and pamphlets relating to international investment and divestment in South Africa.
  - Investment (Box 23, 39)
    - General
    - Netherlands
      - General
      - Shipping Research Bureau
    - United Kingdom
      - General
      - Counter Information Service
      - World Gold Commission
    - World Council of Churches. See Organizations - Religious
  - Divestment - United Kingdom
    - General
    - Anti-Apartheid and Divestment Conference
    - End Loans to Southern Africa (ELTSA). Includes material on Namibia
- UNITED STATES INVESTMENT AND DIVESTMENT IN SOUTH AFRICA, 1976-1987
  Clippings and articles
  - Divestment (Box 24, 39)
    - General
    - American Committee on Africa
    - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO)
    - American Telegraph and Telephone Company (AT & T)
    - Campaign Against Investment in South Africa (CAISA)
    - Coalition for Illinois' Divestment from South Africa (CIDSA)
    - Committee Against Apartheid
    - Committee to Oppose Bank Loans to South Africa (COBLSA - see African Subject Collection)
    - Cornell University
    - Industry Support Unit, Incorporated
    - International Telephone and Telegraph Boycott (ITT Boycott)
    - Polaroid Revolutionary Workers Movement (PRWM)
    - Stanford University
    - United Mine Workers
    - University of Massachusetts
  - Investment
    - General
      - General
      - Report
    - Control Data Corporation
    - Dow Chemical Company
    - General Motors Corporation
    - Hewlett-Packard Company
    - International Business Machines Corporation (IBM)
    - Investor Responsibility Research Center (IRRC)
    - Monsanto International
    - Sullivan principle
      - General
      - Envirotech Corporation
    - United Church Board for World Ministries
    - United Church of Christ
- UNITED STATES UNIVERSITY STUDENT MOVEMENTS, 1977-1989
  Articles, clippings, flyers, newsletters and student newspapers relating to American university student protest of apartheid. Arranged alphabetically by the name of the university.
  - General (Box 25, 39)
  - Amherst College
  - Brown University
  - Columbia University
  - Cornell University
  - Dartmouth College
  - Harvard University
  - Loyola University
  - Northwestern University
  - Princeton University
  - Stanford University
    - General
      - General
      - Clippings (Box 26)
        - 1977 April-December
        - 1978 January-February
        - 1978 March-November
        - 1979-1982
        - 1983-1984
        - 1985 January-May
        - 1985 May (Box 27)
        - 1985 June-October
    - Commission on Investment Responsibility
    - Divestment
    - South Africa - Free Retirement Investment Alternative
    - Stanford Coalition Against Apartheid (SCAA)
    - Stanford Committee for Responsible Investment Policy (SCRIP)
    - Stanford Out of South Africa (SOSA). Includes literature on the "Mandela Free University"
    - Stanford Students for a Free South Africa
    - Student groups
    - Trustees
    - Wells Fargo Bank
  - University of California campuses
    - General. Clippings
    - Berkeley
      - Berkeley's Biko (student publication)
      - Daily Cal (student newspaper) (Box 28, 39)
      - Divestment
      - Educational programs
      - Student protest groups
    - Los Angeles
    - Santa Cruz
  - University of California Regents
  - University of Massachusetts
  - Wesleyan University
  - Yale University
    - General
    - Northeast Conference on the Liberation Struggles in Southern Africa
- DEMOCRATIC RULE, 1994-1995
  Ballot papers, brochures, clippings, correspondence, election reports and updates, fact sheets, flyers, handbook, manuals, newsletters, pamphlets, press release, printed matter, reports, statements, speeches and miscellany relating to the election of 1994 and the process of establishing democratic government in South Africa. See also POLITICAL PARTIES.
  - General (Box 39)
    - General
    - Brochures
    - Correspondence
    - Newsletters
    - Printed matter
    - Press release
    - Reports
    - Speeches
    - Statements
  - Civil service